Let's recap what we've talked
about in the last couple of
lectures to lead into today.
So for policy
gradients, we started
with our first reinforcement
learning algorithm,
where our goal was
to run a policy
to collect a batch of data,
and improve the policy using
that batch of data, and
then repeat this process so
that your approach
can get better
and better with experience.
And the way that we actually
improve the policy using
this data is this
equation that we've
looked at where we collect
samples from the policy.
We then try to increase
the probability for actions
in the data that have a
high reward in the future.
And then we found that if we
subtracted a baseline that's
the average reward, that
encourages us to have the policy
do more of the above average
things and less of the
below average things.
Right now everything
here requires
that the data be sampled
from the exact policy
that you're going to be
taking a gradient step on.
And we talked about how we can
use importance weights this term
right here in order to do
multiple gradient steps so
that we don't have to be
collect a new batch of data
every single time we want
to take one gradient step.
We also talked about
value functions.
And we talked about how a
value for a policy of a state
is the future expected
rewards starting at state S
and following pi thereafter.
And we talked
about a Q function,
which is very similar
to a value function,
except instead of
starting at state s,
you're going to start at state
s and then take action a,
and then follow the policy.
And we can think about
these as follows.
So if we have a
given state that we
want to estimate the
value of for a policy,
then we can run that policy.
And the value is capturing
the expected sum of rewards,
so basically the sum of rewards
of each of these trajectories
averaged over these trajectories
for that state and that policy.
And we can write this as the
summation over future time
steps of our reward if
we're starting at st
and following our policy pi.
And then for the Q function,
instead of starting at s
and running the policy,
we'll start at s,
take a, and then run the policy.
And so we will then be
averaging the sum of rewards
over the trajectories that
were a result of running
the policy after taking
action a at state s.
We can write this as this.
Again, the sum over the
future of the future rewards
conditioning on starting
in state s taking action a,
and then running the
policy in the future.
Great.
Then we also talked about
the advantage function.
And this is,
essentially how much
better is it to take one action
than to follow the policy.
And we can think of
this as the Q function
for that state and
action minus the value
function at that state.
And these are all for
a particular policy pi.
Now to think a little bit
more about intuitively
what value functions
and Q functions mean,
we can take a look at
just one quick example.
So I think I
mentioned in lecture 1
this example of how DeepMind
developed an AI system that
could outperform and
beat the champion at Go,
and this system
was called AlphaGo.
And they used reinforcement
learning to do this.
And if you were to think
about this example,
say the reward is the
outcome of the game,
whether or not
AlphaGo won or lost,
and then the value
function you can
think of as the
expected outcome given
the state of the board and
the policy that's being run.
And so if you have
a better policy,
the value function is
going to be higher.
And likewise, if
you're in a board state
where things are looking
good for that policy,
then you're also going to
have a higher value function.
And so the value function is
influenced both by the policy
and by the state.
And yeah, so that's
an example of what
a value function looks like.
And likewise, a Q
function would be similar,
except instead of running
the policy from the state,
you'd be considering a
particular action first
before running the policy.
So we talked about actor-critic
methods on Friday last week.
And we introduced
this equation, which
looks a lot like
policy gradients
where we're summing
over examples.
Except now, instead of using
the sum of rewards in a given
trajectory, we're using
our estimate of how good
an action is or the advantage.
And this comes from the sum of
rewards which is the Q function,
minus the average sum of
rewards which is the value.
And you can think of this as
being different from policy
gradients, and that we're
estimating which actions
are good and bad, and then
encouraging the policy
to do more of the stuff
that we think is good.
And then we talked about
how to actually estimate
what's good and bad.
This is referred to
as policy evaluation.
And we can fit a value
function, a neural network
that takes as input the state
and outputs a scalar value.
And we fit this as
trying to predict
either just the sum of
rewards or the next reward
plus the value function
where we're bootstrapping off
of our own estimates, or the sum
of a short trajectory of rewards
plus the value
function after that.
And then this
advantage function is
equal to the reward
plus the next value
function minus the
current value function.
So let's get into the
main topic of today,
which is that we talked
about actor-critic methods.
Last week we were
primarily considering
on policy actor-critic methods.
And today we're going to
get into two real algorithms
that people use, PPO and SAC.
And we will start from the
actor-critic formulation
and see how we can make them
off-policy to be more efficient.
And at the end, we'll talk about
how PPO, SAC, and imitation
learning compare to each other.
And yeah, so the
key learning goals
is really the key concepts
behind practical algorithms
like PPO and SAC.
So we have our
actor-critic method.
These are the steps
that we go through
for an on-policy actor-critic
method where we sample data,
fit rewards with our
value function, then
we estimate the advantage with
this equation here for all
of our states and actions
in this set of data,
then we estimate what the
gradient of our policy is
and update our gradient.
Now, if we want to be able to
take multiple gradient steps,
we need to be able to
evaluate our gradient not just
at the current policy
that collected the data--
but, for example,
after we take step 5,
we're now going to have
a new set of parameters
that were different from what
was collected the data in step
1.
And so what we're
going to do is we're
going to use importance weights,
which we saw in the policy
gradient lecture.
And so our new
objective is going to--
or our new gradient is going
to look a little bit different.
So say that we collected
data with pi theta.
Now we've taken a gradient step,
and we have pi theta prime.
So we want to be
able to evaluate
the gradient of the
objective at theta prime.
And to do this, we
will reuse the data
that we collected from
pi theta in step 1.
And we're then going to use the
same gradient step as before,
but we're going to weight the
gradient term with an importance
ratio that is a ratio
between our new policy
pi theta prime, and the policy
that was used to collect
the data which is pi theta.
So this is our importance
weight term right here.
And the rest will
look the same as
before where we'll be
evaluating the gradient of log
pi times the advantage
or advantage estimate.
This advantage estimate
will still be for the policy
before taking a
gradient step pi theta,
and this will be for
the s, a pair here.
So this is our new gradient.
So that's here.
Now, in principle,
once we've done this,
this means that we can take
multiple gradient steps.
So we can sample a batch
of data once and then
fit our advantage estimates,
and then compute our gradient,
take a gradient step, and
then recompute our gradient,
take a gradient
step, and so forth.
And the only thing
that's going to change
as we take more gradient steps
is this importance weight here.
And of course
we'll be doing back
propagation on
our new parameters
rather than our old parameters.
And then our advantage
estimates will still
be based off of the old policy.
Now, there's something
that can go wrong here.
And to see what
can go wrong, it's
helpful to actually look
at the surrogate objective.
Right now we're
looking at the gradient
that we're going to be applying.
But when we actually
implement this in practice,
we'll be having some
surrogate objective
that we construct
in order to use
auto differentiation to get the
gradients for free from PyTorch.
And so if we were to write
down the surrogate objective
for this, we need to
formulate some objectives such
that the gradient of
our surrogate objective
is equal to this right here.
Now, to do that, we
can remember that we
have this convenient
identity where
probability times the
grad log of a probability
is equal to the gradient of
the original probability.
This is the same log trick
that we've been seeing.
We used to formulate the
original policy gradient
objective.
And the way this
comes in handy is
that we actually see this
pi grad log pi right here.
And so this means that this
is equal to the gradient of pi
theta prime.
And if we want to then construct
a surrogate objective such
that its gradient is this,
then the surrogate objective
is simply going to be--
we can replace this with
pi theta of a given s.
And then we'll still have
the other terms pi theta,
and the advantage right here.
Well, let's just say
this is just over i,
all the examples
are in our batch.
And so the way that
I formulated this
is the gradient of this
surrogate objective
is equal to this right here.
And we see that if we take the
gradient of this with respect
to theta prime, we get grad
theta prime right here.
And the gradient of
theta prime of pi
is equal to pi theta prime
times grad log pi theta prime.
So you can see
this on the slides.
So here's our surrogate
objective right here.
Now, if we look at the
surrogate objective--
so the policy is
going to be trying
to maximize this when we take
gradient steps on our policy.
And if we're trying to
maximize this objective,
we have our advantage estimates.
And so the thing that the
policy will want to do
is it will probably want to take
the advantage estimates that
are positive and increase the
probability of our actions
for those, especially if
there are actions that
had very low probability
that we want to increase this
a lot so that we can get a
very high ratio here, such
that we can increase the
likelihood of actions
for high advantages.
And then for
negative advantages,
we'll want to decrease
the probability.
Now, this all seems
reasonable here.
The thing that's a
little bit tricky
is that these
advantages are still
based off of the old policy.
And they were estimated based
on a single batch of data.
And so if you take too
many gradient steps
on this surrogate objective,
it means you might actually,
in some ways, overfit.
You might be using
these advantages
at some point when
they become out of date
and may no longer be
applicable to your new policy.
And so basically the
challenge that can come up
is you might get really
unstable learning.
As a rough visual
for what this might
look like is if you
were to plot the--
let's say that this is
the number of examples
of state actions that
you've collected,
and then the y-axis
is the rewards
that your policy is seeing
over the course of learning
as it collects more data.
If you take only one gradient
step for every batch of data
that you collect,
then your learning
might look something
like this, where
it learns very slowly because
you can only take one gradient
step for each batch
of data, and that
means that it's going to take
many, many data points in order
to learn.
So this is for
one gradient step.
Now, say, you maybe
increase this a little bit,
so you take five
gradient steps, then
you should learn a
little bit faster.
So maybe you learn
something like this
because you're taking more
gradient steps per data point.
So with respect to the amount
of data that you're collecting,
your reward should
increase more.
But then if you try to
get a little bit greedy
and do a lot more gradient
steps on this objective,
you might start to
overfit your advantages.
And you'll get something
where maybe you'll actually
start to increase
reward very quickly,
but then learning might be
unstable, and at some point
it might even collapse
because your policy will
overfit those advantages.
You'll get some
really bad policy,
or a policy that is increased
the probability to 1
for some advantage but done so
in a way that makes the policy
performance poor.
And so this would be--
I don't know exactly how many
gradient steps this would be,
but this would be more
gradient steps than the others.
And this would be to many
gradient steps essentially.
So the question is, what is the
behavior of an overfit policy
look like in practice?
It really depends
on the problem.
As one example, if it's
overfitting quite a bit,
it might try to be assigning
a very, very high probability
to one particular
action that has
a high advantage in the data.
And when it does that,
it might actually also
increase the probability
of other actions
around it just because neural
networks are somewhat smooth.
And when you do that, it might
be a very deterministic policy
that no longer explores.
I don't know exactly
what would happen,
but if you had a 2D agent
that's moving around in a grid,
and maybe your goal
is to get here,
then a good policy
would go here.
And a policy that's overfit, I
would expect to potentially--
maybe, for example, it
learns that going right
is good but doesn't figure out
that you need to stop here.
And does it figure out
that you need to go up?
Then what the overfit
policy might do
is it might take a
straight line here and then
keep on trying to go
roughly in this direction
and then end up in the
corner because it's
overfit to one batch of data
that told it to go this way
but didn't figure out
that it needs to stop.
Yeah, exactly.
So this is 5 gradient
steps on five loops of this
before you then collect
a new batch of data
and then refit your
value function.
Currently it's refit only on
the current batch of data.
Later this lecture, we'll
see how we can potentially
reuse previous batches.
So the question is,
what is the importance
of using the surrogate objective
versus the original formulation?
This is the same formulation.
I think it's a little
bit more intuitive if you
look at the surrogate
objective to understand
that these importance weights
are really trying to make it--
it's very easy to
increase the probability.
You can also see that
with the gradient
as well, where it's
going to be trying
to increase the probability.
But I think it's just
a little bit easier
to see with the
surrogate objective.
We also, in a minute,
see how we can
change the surrogate objective,
and it gets a little bit more
complicated.
PPO looks a little
bit more complicated
if you look at the
gradient versus if you look
at the surrogate objective.
So the question is, why are we
using the importance weights
to evaluate the gradient?
So this importance
weight term is
what is allowing us to
do more than one gradient
step in the first place.
And it's what's
allowing this blue curve
to do better in some ways.
If you don't have the
importance weights,
then it's essentially
not allowing
you to accurately
estimate the gradient
on the old batch of data.
So what happens when the
a network is too old?
The advantage
estimates are going
to be based off of
some batch of data.
It's not like infinite.
It's going to be a batch
of data that might be--
I don't know, around a few
thousand time steps of data.
And those advantage they're
also under the old policy
before we took any
gradient steps.
And so if you take a
lot of gradient steps
on this objective,
those advantages
they're only true
for the old policy.
And they're also only based
off of a limited batch of data.
And primarily because they were
based off of the old policy,
after you've taken, I
don't 50 gradient steps
or 100 gradient steps,
they become out of date.
In this example, it's
possible that your old policy
right here maybe it did actually
decide to go up, for example.
So then you learned that
if you're over here,
you should go this
way because later you
will go up because that's what
your advantages are telling you.
But then in practice, once
you have your new policy,
in the future you'll be
doing something different.
And so those
advantages over here
are no longer accurate,
no longer valid.
And you need to collect
a new batch of data
under your new policy in order
to have accurate advantages.
So the policy is going to
increase probability on actions
with high advantages.
These advantages are
based on the old policy,
and so they'll get out of date.
And so if you take a
lot of gradient steps,
the policy is really--
The other thing that
I didn't mention
is that when it's
increasing the probability,
it's also inherently trying
to differ significantly
from the old policy.
It's not only encouraged
to increase probability
on advantages, but
that is going to cause
it to change drastically
from the old policy,
and this means because
you're also changing a lot,
these advantages are even
less likely to be up to date
with your current policy.
And so there's a question
of how do we address this.
And there's actually
a couple of things
that we can do in order to
actually be able to stably take
more gradient steps.
And the key idea is if
we keep the new policy
to be a little bit more
close to the original policy,
then those advantage estimates
are more likely to be valid.
And there's two ways
in which we might
be able to encourage
the new policy to be
similar to the old one.
One would be to add a term to
our surrogate objective that
explicitly is going
to try to encourage
the policies to be similar.
And these policies
are representing
distributions over actions.
And so one way that
we could do that
is to add a term
to our objective.
So we have our surrogate
objective right here.
If we have it be equal to
the same thing as what's
written up there,
let's call this,
I don't know, con
for constrained.
This is going to be equal to
the original surrogate objective
that we're trying to maximize.
And then we can
add a penalty that
discourages you
from changing too
much from the previous policy.
And that penalty could take
the form of the KL divergence
between two distributions.
So this could be
the KL divergence
between the new policy
distribution and the old policy
distribution.
And so if we add this to our
surrogate objective, what
this will do is it'll encourage
the policies to stay close
to one another while you
take more gradient steps,
and so your advantage functions
will be more accurate,
and this will allow you to more
stably take more gradient steps.
Now, it will still be
constraining your step size.
And so it's a little
bit of a balance.
But essentially the results of
something like this in principle
should look--
I'm out of colors--
maybe should look
something like this
if you do more gradient steps
but with this KL penalty.
So the comment was, it's
incentivizing because
of this ratio right here, and
it's controlling the upper part.
The lower part is fixed.
This is the old policy.
It's controlling this new one.
And so it can make this
very large or very small,
and that will cause these
weights to either go to 0
or become--
or potentially be
infinite, depending
on how small the old
policy probability was.
And when we constrain
how different these are,
then we're encouraging this
to be closer to one answer.
So you can't just
push this to infinity,
or you can't just push it to 0.
So a couple comments were here.
So the first was that, to
do this scale constraint,
we actually need to keep around
our old parameters in memory.
This can actually
be annoying to do.
It increases your memory costs.
And this is actually
not uncommon to do
with large language models.
And you'll have to keep
around the full set of weights
for your old language
model in order to do this.
That said, there are ways
to potentially cache this.
So you potentially
could just keep around
the probabilities that were
assigned to different states
for a given batch of data.
And then the second
note was that,
for this surrogate objective,
this ratio is initially
going to be one.
And then once you take
one gradient step,
that's where this
starts to diverge.
The goal is to basically
constrain how much you're
changing the policy and only to
change the policy a little bit
rather than a ton.
One other way to
think about this
is if your policy is a
neural network that's
taking as input like
images, for example,
you're going to need a
lot of gradient steps
in order to change the
features of those images.
And so you want to be able to
take a lot of gradient steps,
but without substantially
changing the action distribution
that the policy is going to
take so that you can still
refine your features without
causing this objective
to overfit too much.
So the question is,
how do we encourage
it to change a little
bit, but not too much.
Oftentimes you'll have
some hyperparameter
that is in front of
this KL divergence
that needs to be tuned.
And so this beta is
like a hyperparameter.
And this will control how much
you're allowing it to shift.
This ends up being oftentimes a
fairly important hyperparameter
when you use KL constraints.
At the same time, you
don't need to tune it.
Usually people tune it
within an order of magnitude
rather than very carefully
finding point 4, 2, 3, whatever.
So the question was,
how does this look
like for the original
gradient and not quite
understanding the surrogate?
So the surrogate
objective is what
we're plugging into PyTorch.
And then PyTorch or
TensorFlow or JAX
will then compute
the gradients for us.
And when they compute
the gradients for us,
they will get the first line.
The gradient of the second line
is equal to the first line.
If you were to
implement this, you
have your original
surrogate objective
and then you just plug-in
this term as well.
You can look up the expression
for KL divergence between two
categorical distributions
or two Gaussians,
which in the Gaussian case
will be a function of the means
and variances.
And then just add that to
your surrogate objective
and then have PyTorch
give you the gradients.
If you write down the equation
for a particular distribution,
you could also get
the gradients yourself
if you want to take
a look at that.
What's the difference between
J theta and J tilde theta?
So I'm using J tilde to refer
to the surrogate objective
because it's technically
not the true objective.
The original J
theta objective was
equal to the expected
sum of rewards.
So it was the sum
of rewards here.
So this is an
estimation of that.
So the first idea is
use a KL constraint.
This is actually
very common to do.
We will leave it
at this for now.
We'll actually won't
use KL constraints.
There is actually a version of
PPO that uses KL constraints,
but it's not the
most common version.
But it's also used a lot
in preference optimization,
so we'll probably see it
again in a couple of weeks.
And then there's
actually a second idea.
So we could add this
constraint in the objective.
for this ratio right
here, we could simply
remove the incentive
for the policy
to change this ratio a lot.
And the way that we
would do that is we
could actually just
clip this ratio
so that the ratio never
exceeds some value
and never goes below some value.
And so what that
would look like is--
I guess this is version 1.
What version 2 would
look like is we
would be taking these
importance weights,
and we would be clipping them.
So we have the importance
weights, pi theta prime
divided by pi theta.
And we'd be clipping these
to be between some lower
value, 1 minus epsilon, and some
higher value, 1 plus epsilon.
Epsilon could be
something like 0.2.
So you're saying that if
it goes below 0.8, then
it'll just be 0.8.
And if this goes
above 1.2, we're
just going to leave it as 1.2.
Now, this is a
little bit informal.
If I were to write this
out mathematically,
what this would look like.
Let's call this w.
This weight right here.
Then if we wanted to clip
it below by 1 minus epsilon,
then we would be taking the max
between w and 1 minus epsilon.
And if we wanted to then clip
this above by 1 plus epsilon,
then we would be taking the min
between this and 1 plus epsilon.
And now, if we use
this clipped importance
weights in our
objective right here,
once the policy changes
the ratio to be above 1.2,
it's no longer
going to be able--
increasing the probability any
further isn't going to help it.
It's no longer going
to be incentivized
to increase the
probability further
because the objective will just
stay as 1.2 times the advantage.
And so it isn't actually
explicitly constraining
the policy not to
change, but it's
removing the incentive
to change significantly
from the old policy.
Yes.
So it cannot be below
1 minus epsilon,
and it cannot be
above 1 plus epsilon.
A value of epsilon
that's used in practice
it might be something like 0.2.
So it's not tiny.
Sometimes you refer to
epsilon as tiny numbers.
In this case, it's
going to be constraining
it to be between 0.8 and 1.2.
So this idea of bounding
the importance weights
is one of the key
ideas behind PPO, which
is a popular RL algorithm.
And so let's see.
If we were to then put this
clipping into practice,
we could take our
surrogate objective,
and then replace the
importance weights
by the clipped
right here in order to get a
modified surrogate objective.
Now, there's a
couple more tricks
that PPO introduces to try
to get stable reinforcement
learning improvement.
So in this first
trick, it's no longer
incentivized to
deviate significantly.
Now, one thing that's a little
bit funky about these importance
weights is that there is
actually a possibility
that it might actually--
the clipping in some
rare cases might actually
make the objective better.
If, for example,
the policy ended up
assigning a very low probability
to a negative advantage,
and it went below
the advantages, then
you're clipping it
to a higher weight.
And so one thing that PPO does
and the final objective of PPO
is to take this
clipped objective,
but take the
minimum with respect
to the original objective.
And this minimum
is just making sure
that the clipping will never
make the objective better.
It ensures that this is a lower
bound on the original surrogate
objective.
And this means that we're
going to be maximizing a lower
bound on our objective.
And usually, if
you're ever going
to be optimizing or
maximizing something that's
different from your
original objective,
it's good if it's a lower bound
because it means that you're
actually going to be--
you're not going to be
maximizing something
that you can maximize beyond
the original objective.
So this is the final
PPO surrogate objective.
The motivation behind
trick 1 or trick 2?
Trick 2.
So the motivation
behind trick 2.
I'm not actually sure how
often this happens in practice,
how critical this is,
but the motivation
is that you might
actually be in a scenario
where maybe it increased
the probability
on a lot of the good stuff.
It decreased the probability
on a lot of the bad stuff.
But in some of the rare
circumstances where
maybe increasing the
probability on a good stuff
led it-- there was
another advantage that
had a similar state that
was actually really bad,
and maybe it increased the
probability on both of those,
in that case, clipping it
at 1.2 for that second one
is actually making it better.
It's actually making the
objective better because you're
then saying, OK,
maybe it assigned
to a really high probability
to this bad action,
we're then going to clip that
at 1.2 or something like that.
And so if we take the
minimum with respect
to the original objective,
the state action level,
at the data point
level, this is going
to ensure that those
situations aren't happening.
And so I guess, explicitly say
you have a particular state
and action pair where the
advantage is, I don't know,
negative 1000 or something like
that, so something really large.
And say that your new policy
for this state and action
decided to give it a probability
of 0.9 or something very high.
And the original policy maybe
gave it a probability of--
oops.
If the original policy gave
it a probability of 0.1,
then, in this case, the
ratio between these two is 9.
And then when we clip it, it
then would be clipped to 1.2.
And then once we
clip it to 1.2, we'll
multiply 1.2 by negative 1000.
And so that's actually going to
be making the objective better
than if we hadn't
clipped the objective.
And so what this
trick number 2 does
is it means that
it actually doesn't
get to do the clipping for
this particular data point.
And this will disincentivize
it from making these accidents,
which is a good thing to do.
So you're asking, why don't
we just clip above and not
clip below?
So there is actually an
analogous version of this,
if you just make this
negative and flip
these, where the clipping could
also make the objective better.
For example, if a Hertz for a
given state and action pair is
positive 1,000, and the
new policy assigns 0.1,
and the old policy assigns 0.9,
if you did this by accident,
or if it happened to do this
when optimizing other data
points, then now the ratio
is going to be 1 over 9,
which is very small.
You multiply that by 1,000.
If you clip the 1 over 9
by 0.8, that's actually
be making the objective better.
And so generally
clipping on both sides
and then taking the lower bound
prevents both of these scenarios
from being encouraged
through clipping.
So this is the final
PPO surrogate objective.
The last trick that PPO does
is on estimating the advantage.
So to estimate the
advantage, there's
a third trick that's used.
This is actually a
trick where I'm not sure
how necessary it is myself.
I haven't done a
ton of comparisons.
And the way that it
works is you still
can be fitting a value function
V pi in the normal way,
either with Monte
Carlo or bootstrapping.
But then once you fit
that value function,
previously, the equation
for our value function
was the reward plus the next
value minus the current value.
And instead of just
using a horizon of 1,
it's actually going to
use a varying horizon.
So before we were estimating
the advantage of a given
state and action, we're using
the reward at that state
plus the value at the
next state minus the value
at the current state.
These were all for pi, and
then had hats on each of these.
But you can also
estimate the advantage
using something that looks like
n step returns, where you're
actually going to be summing
over multiple of the rewards
into the future or adding that
future value instead of adding
just one step into the future.
We were talking about
bias and variance before.
If you calculate these different
advantages with varying horizons
and then weight
them accordingly,
then you can get
advantage estimates that
have varying variance
and maybe have less bias
than if you just use the one
step estimate right here.
I think there's some argument
in terms of bias and variance
that can be made.
But it's also not 100% clear if
it's necessary in my opinion.
So there's now going to be a
hyperparameter here with regard
to how do you choose
these weights with regard
to the different n step returns.
Generally, you'll mostly
use the earlier ones
so that you have less variance.
And usually you will choose
it to decay very quickly
as the horizon increases.
So you're mostly still
going to be using
the t equals 1 or n equals 1.
So if you're using these
weights, do you set gamma to 1
or do you use them together?
You'll use them together.
And if you write
this out, you'll
get a term that multiplies
gamma and lambda here.
So the question was, is this
the same as taking a weighted
average of different n step
returns for different n's.
So the one thing
that's different
is we're still going to be
fitting the value function
in the normal way, and then
this is in terms of how
we estimate the advantage.
But otherwise you can think
of it as n step returns,
but averaging the different ends
in order to get an estimate.
What's the benefit of using GAE?
I think it's a little
bit hard to motivate.
I think one way to view it is
that if you just use this one
step return, especially if
the time steps are very close
together, then this might be--
if your V's are not
completely accurate,
then this estimate
might be a bit off.
And if you increase
this horizon,
then you'll get potentially
a better estimate.
Now, why not just use one
value of n versus a mixture?
Perhaps it helps you
hedge a little bit
if you're not sure which
value of n is correct.
But I don't have a great
motivation myself for it.
If you use it and
don't use it, I'm
not 100% sure what the
performance is like.
So the final PPO algorithm.
We sample a batch of data.
We fit a value
function to that data,
and then we evaluate this
generalized advantage estimate
that we just talked about.
And then we will
update the policy
by taking M gradient steps
on your surrogate objective
where the surrogate
objective uses
these clipped importance
weights using the GAE estimate
of the advantage function.
And then you can
repeat this process
after taking M gradient steps,
then sample a new batch of data,
fit a new value function to
that, and repeat the process.
In order to get a rough sense
for what this looks like,
here are some example
hyperparameters.
Now, generally
hyperparameters are something
that you would tune per domain.
So this is not like my
recommended hyperparameters
necessarily, but just
to give a rough sense
for what this looks like.
The batch of data might have
around 2000 time steps in it.
So if you have a long horizon
problem that has 1,000 time
steps, this might actually be
only a couple trajectories.
If you have a shorter
horizon problem,
this might be more trajectories.
When you update the
policy on step 4,
a common hyperparameter
is something
around 10 epochs on the data set
that was collected in step 1.
And if your batch
size is 64, this
might be around
300 gradient steps.
And so this means that
in comparison to before,
because we introduced
this clipping,
we're actually able to take 300
gradient steps without having
really unstable improvement.
So that's good.
Clipping range.
I mentioned 0.2 is something
that might be reasonable.
And then you might run this
full outer loop 500 times
in order to get around a million
total time steps of experience.
We'll see some other examples,
actually some cooler examples
at the end of the lecture.
But if you run PPO
on this very simple
simulated the right half
of a cheetah or something,
and you look at, as you collect
more time steps of data,
what does the reward look like?
There are a number
of algorithms here.
This beige one is
vanilla policy gradient.
It's a slightly smarter version
of vanilla policy gradient,
but it's basically vanilla
policy gradient where you're not
fitting the advantage
function, and you're not
doing the clipping.
And then PPO is up here.
And you can see that with less
experience able to improve
much faster because it's
fitting the advantage function,
and because it's doing the
clipping on the gradient
in order to take many more
gradient steps on a single data
point.
So can I explain the
error from 4 to 1
and how are the
parameters being updated?
So this error is just saying
that after we finish step four,
then we're going to go
back to step 1 and collect
a new batch of data.
When we do that,
we're going to keep
our policy as it was at
the current time step
and keep on iterating.
And so at this
point actually theta
will become the
previous theta prime,
and you'll be sampling a batch
of data from your latest policy.
And then the other thing here is
that, for this value function,
you could warm started at
the previous value function
or you could train
it from scratch.
It depends a little
bit on the domain.
So in terms of these
plots, the question is,
do you fit the best set of
hyperparameters and then run it?
So each of them will have its
own set of hyperparameters.
And the best practice is to
figure out good hyperparameters
on one environment or
maybe two environments,
and then apply those
hyperparameters
to the remaining environments
in your experiments.
There are scenarios
where you might
need a new set of
hyperparameters
for a different domain.
For example, if you are
controlling something
at 1 Hertz versus 5 Hertz,
or optimizing a language
model versus a half
cheetah, the hyperparameters
will be different.
So there is some
variability there.
One good practice is to not
tune your hyperparameters
per environment because
then you're essentially
using more data,
more samples in order
to get those hyperparameters
in the first place,
and that wouldn't be reflected
on this curve right here.
We should move on.
But happy to answer
it after class.
So far we've talked about
using one batch of data
for one gradient step that's
the fully on policy version.
And we've looked at using
one batch of policy data
for multiple gradient steps.
And this is off-policy.
What I'd like to talk about
for the rest of the lecture
is can we be even
more off-policy.
So can we reuse
previous batches of data
rather than recollecting
a new batch each time,
like all of the past trial
and error experience.
And there's two
ideas for doing this.
One is that we actually need
to retain all of our past data.
We'll use a term called a
replay buffer that you actually
saw in homework 1, where we will
have a data set of past data.
We'll keep on adding to it.
And at some point, we might
also remove some very old data
from it.
This is called a replay buffer
because you're replaying
your past experiences.
And then the second
idea is we actually
need to adjust some
of the equations
to remove some on
policy assumptions
in order to be able to actually
use all of our past data.
So what this looks like is we'll
take our actor critic algorithm.
But to make it off-policy,
we can think about it
as getting one time step of
data, then updating our policy,
getting another time
step, updating our policy,
and so forth.
So rather than getting one
batch and then doing updates,
we can actually do
this much more online.
And when we update our
policy, this will actually
be coming from a replay buffer.
We'll be actually
doing gradient steps
using all of our
past experiences
rather than just our
immediate past experience.
When we collect
experience, we'll
want to then add this
to our replay buffer.
And when we then
update our policy,
we want to use a minibatch
sampled from all previous data
rather than just our
last batch of data.
So that's the modifications
we need to make in order
to use a replay buffer.
So walking through this, we
start with an empty replay
buffer.
We then collect experience
from our policy.
We add that to
the replay buffer,
and then we sample a
transition state action
reward and next state.
From the replay buffer,
there's a small probability
this could be exactly
what we just sampled,
but otherwise it'll be
something randomly sampled
from our previous experience.
Then we'll update our value
function using the batch of data
that we just sampled
from the buffer.
We can update our value function
with the same objective before
but now we're going to be
averaging over our minibatch.
And then we can
evaluate the advantage,
and then take a gradient
step on our policy.
So that's the mechanics
of replay buffers.
Finally update the policy
and then repeat this process.
Unfortunately, this algorithm
right now is currently broken.
And it's broken in
two different ways.
The first way that's
broken is right here.
So say that we're
using bootstrapping
to update our value
function, then
our target would be the reward
at the current time step
plus our value estimate
for the next state.
And so I have a
question for you.
And the question is, when
we're fitting a value function
on all of the data
in the replay buffer,
so this is the data from all
of our previous policies,
the question is, what policy
are we learning a value function
for when we fit the value
function this way from data
in a replay buffer?
And so I'll give you two
minutes to discuss that
and then we'll come back.
Let's come back.
I also should have
maybe mentioned
that the answer is not as
clean as some other questions.
So the response there was the--
so for our latest policy,
we actually don't have any--
we have maybe one data
point from that policy.
the rest of the buffer
is not from that policy.
And so we don't actually have
any really much data at all
from our current policy.
So it's not our current policy.
And that's why
this is incorrect.
And in particular, when
we collect trajectories
from previous policies, the
actions will be different,
and that means that the
next state will also
be different when you took that
action as well as the reward.
So the policy that you're
going to be learning a value
function for--
I'll phrase it
slightly differently.
The policy that you'll be
learning a value function for
is some mixture of all
of your past policies.
It's actually not
trivial to write it down.
If things were collected
in a particular way,
the policy might look
something like an average
over your previous policies,
if you had N previous policies.
Now, it's actually a little
bit different than this
because in some
states one policy
might have gone over
here, and another policy
might have gone over here.
And so then in this
state, it's going
to be a mixture of policies.
But in this state, it's going
to be more of this policy.
In this state it's going
to be a different policy.
So it's actually a
little bit messy.
But the thing
that's definitive is
that it's not going
to be a value function
for your current policy.
And we would like to get a value
function for our current policy
using data from
previous policies
so that we can actually
estimate this advantage
for our current policy and
get an accurate gradient
for our current policy.
It's a little bit
messy, but it's
a policy that is
a conglomeration
of your previous
policies or some mixture
of your previous policies.
It's not something that you
can very cleanly write down,
but it's a mixture
of your past policy.
The other thing that's
a bit wrong about this
is that here this is
also not the action
that the policy
would have taken.
And likewise, when you pass
the action into the advantage,
that's also not the action that
the policy would have taken.
And so we'll also see
how we can fix that part.
But first, let's talk
about the value function.
And we have this
key question of,
how do we fit a value function
for our current policy using
a replay buffer of data
from past policies?
So one idea here is,
instead of trying to fit V,
what if we try to
fit Q instead of V?
So we can remember
that the Q function
it's very similar to
the value function,
but it's the sum of rewards if
we start at s and take action a.
So you can think of it as the
sum over say, this is St of at.
This is the sum of time
steps starting at t
through the end of the
trajectory of the reward m
r of St prime at prime under
the expectation that we're
running our policies after
taking state St and action at.
And so this under the
expectation of pi theta
conditioned on St, at.
So this is just the
definition of the Q function.
So we have the summation
over future time steps.
We can start to write
out the summation.
And in particular, if we
write out the first time step,
the first state and action
is actually just St,
at because that's what we're
passing into the Q function.
So we can write this as, we know
the reward of the first state
and action that we
took, and then we
could have a summation over
things starting at t plus 1
of the sum of future rewards.
Now, for this sum
of future rewards,
this would now need to be
an expectation after St, at.
And so for this
one, we would need
an expectation if we were
starting from St plus 1
under the dynamics, and
remaining actions and states
sampled from pi theta.
This is for pi theta.
Now, this is starting to look
also a lot like a value function
but for the St plus 1.
And so you can actually also
write this in terms of Q.
And in particular,
you can write this
is equivalent to the reward at
the current time step plus--
if we then try to take
this one step further,
then we'll have St plus 1
sampled by the dynamics,
and at plus 1 sampled
from our policy.
So if we have the
expectation over St plus 1
and at plus 1 sampled
from our policy,
then the Q at the
current time step
is the reward plus this
expectation of the next Q.
And so we can essentially
define Q recursively
like this as the reward
at the current time
step plus the future Q
at the next time step.
And the thing that's really
nice about this equation
is that this equation holds
for any state in action.
We haven't made any assumption
about which state and action
the data was collected for.
And so if we walk through
that on the slides again.
So we have data points that are
state action reward next state.
This is sampled from
some other policy,
and we also have
the future reward.
This is a trajectory
collected from an old policy.
This action was taken
from the past policy.
And this future reward depends
on the past policies actions.
We don't want to use the
future reward part because this
is going to depend on the past
policy actions in a pretty
complicated way.
But if we're fitting
Q of s, a, then we're
actually passing
the action as input,
and it's actually
OK if that action
is a bit different from what
our policy would have taken.
And so because that's
OK, and because we
have this equation that
represents this recursion,
then we can actually
try to fit Qa
to a target that
looks like this.
And so we have our
definition of the Q function
of the future
rewards conditioned
on the state and action.
And for any state and action,
we have this equivalence
where Q for pi theta of s, a is
the reward at the current time
step plus the Q function
at the next time step
where you have an expectation
over the next time step,
and an expectation over the
next action for a policy.
Yeah.
Good question.
So the question was, for this
data, we have this action.
And for the Q function,
it takes as input
an action but the
rest of the trajectory
was still following
a different policy.
And the Q needs to
be like-- we need
to be summing the rewards
for a current policy
not the other policy.
And the thing that
we've done here
is that if we represent
this Q in terms
of Q for our current policy,
this second term right here
is actually not using
the future data at all.
Well, the S prime we
will be using the data,
but it's not using
anything after S prime.
And in particular, we're using
our bootstrap estimate of Q
at the next time step.
And for the next action,
instead of using the action that
was taken in our data, we
can use the action sampled
from our current policy.
So we're recursively
defining the Q function here,
and the only things
that will-- maybe we
can actually just go
through the next part.
So what we'll do here is
we'll sample an s, a, s
prime from the buffer.
This a was from an old policy,
but the dynamics are constant.
And then we'll sample an a
prime from our current policy.
This is sampled from our current
policy conditioned on s prime.
And then we can
estimate the q function
as the reward at the
current time step
plus the q function for the
next state in the buffer,
and an action sampled
from our policy here.
And because this action
is sampled from our policy
rather than from
the data set, then
we're actually
getting an estimate
for our current
policies Q function.
So yeah.
Good question.
So the question was,
does this require
that we see data from all
possible state action pairs?
There is a very
good insight there.
We don't actually need to see
data from all state action
pairs, but it means that, for
this target to be accurate,
we do need to have
data that covers
actions that are similar to
what our policy would be taking.
And if we haven't
seen that data,
this Q function is
going to be inaccurate.
And you'll need to collect
data from your current policy
in order to get that.
We're not getting a really
good estimate of our Q function
for free based on past policies.
We still need decent coverage of
what our policy would have done,
but it provides somewhat
of a means to use old data.
And so I guess just
to finish the slide
and then come back
to that point,
we'll be using r plus
gamma times Q as our label.
And then we can use
supervised learning
to pass as input to the state
and action to a neural network,
and then try to output
this label right here.
And again, we can
use a similar like L2
error between our
prediction and the target,
just like with the
value function.
And to be accurate,
these targets
need to have sufficient action
coverage and need to have--
the action taken
from your policy
can't be wildly out
of distribution,
otherwise these targets
will be inaccurate.
Yeah.
So we'll need to have taken
that action from that state.
And so this does
make it, if you don't
have any data from that
state, that's a problem.
And then if you have
data from that state
but only for very different
actions is also a problem.
Some of this is also
going to be relying on,
neural networks can generalize,
can interpolate reasonably well,
and so that helps this.
But you do need sufficient
coverage for this
to be accurate.
So we actually didn't quite get
to this equation on the board.
We have this expectation
here over the next state
and an action sampled
from our policy.
And this equation estimates
this with a single sample
where we have St and at.
And then we're going
to use the St plus 1
from our data set,
which is just one
example to estimate this part.
And then in this equation,
we'll use one sample, at plus 1
in order to estimate this.
There are actually methods that
you can use multiple samples
to estimate this to get a better
estimate of this expectation.
In a batch, you'll be sampling
from your current policy.
Each data point will
get a different sample,
so you also get multiple
samples in that way.
But yeah, even
for next state you
could also sample
multiple actions here.
So we mentioned that we need
sufficient action coverage here.
And the question was, if we use
a KL constraint or something
similar to encourage it to stay
close to the previous policy,
would that be helpful here?
And I think that one of the
algorithms that we'll see
doesn't do that, but
it's a good idea.
And in general, we'll see that
those KL constraints come up
quite frequently in
reinforcement learning
because we'll often be assuming
that we're not deviating too
far from our previous policy.
And yeah, it's possible
for the algorithm
that we'll see that
could make it better
in some circumstances too.
Well, so I guess what
we talked about is
we'll be updating Q hat with our
targets y, where the target is
r plus the Q. And
critically, the state Si
will be sampled from
the replay buffer.
But the next action will not
be from the replay buffer.
It will be sampled from
our policy conditioned
on that next state
from the buffer.
So that will be our revised
step 3 for the algorithm.
The last thing is what
we want to do here.
So instead of estimating
the value function,
we estimate the Q function.
There's a couple of things that
we'll do here for this update.
The first is that it'll
be convenient to use
Q instead of a.
And this means that we're
not going to use a baseline.
This is going to
be higher variance,
but that's going to
be OK because we're
going to be using
a lot more data,
all the data from our
buffer, not just the data
from our current policy.
And then the second is that
the current policy's actions
are likely better than
the past policy's actions.
And so for this
update right here,
we'll be sampling an a
from our current policy
instead from the action
taken in the buffer.
And then this will be the
gradient update on our policy
where we'll be looking at log
pi of a given s times Q of s, a.
And these a's will be
sampled from our policy.
So essentially using the same
trick as what we did with the Q
function, except now
for the current state
instead of the next state.
So here's our full algorithm.
There's one remaining
problem, which
is that the states
in our buffer didn't
come from our current policy.
There isn't really anything
that we can do here.
But it's actually not
necessarily a bad thing.
It means that we're going to be
getting a policy on a broader
state distribution rather than
just on the state distribution
that our policy would visit.
So this is essentially the
soft actor-critic algorithm.
There are other ways to estimate
this gradient that we don't have
time to get into today,
but we might go over
in future lectures.
There are also some
fancier ways to fit this Q
function that we'll see
in the next lecture.
But the algorithm here that
this is very, very close to
is called soft
actor-critic or SAC.
And if we compare SAC and PPO,
the more off-policy version
that uses a replay buffer
is shown in orange,
and the less off-policy
is shown in brown.
And so we see that we're able
to get much more data efficient
learning with something
like SAC than with something
that's less off-policy.
So you can be far, far
more data efficient
when you use this replay buffer.
The downside is that
it can be a lot harder
to tune hyperparameters,
and generally it
can be a bit less stable
when you're using these Q
functions than compared to PPO.
Cool.
And then lastly, when
you're fully off-policy,
you can actually
be efficient enough
to run reinforcement
learning on real robots.
So in this example,
in about two hours,
the policy learns how to walk
forward just with the algorithm
that we talked about.
You can also learn some
cool manipulation tasks
with reinforcement learning.
This was seeded
with demonstrations.
This is a very precise task.
And you can see that
actually, if you compare
the performance
of this RL method,
it actually gets 100% on all
the tasks that they tested.
Whereas if you use
imitation learning,
you'll get a much
lower success rate.
And reinforcement learning
also leads to a faster policy
than with imitation learning.
And then PPO is a
common algorithm
that's used if you want really
stable learning but less data
efficient learning.
And so if you're in
simulation, for example,
data is not a problem.
You can collect tons and
tons of data in simulation.
And you can learn a
policy in simulation.
And then if you carefully
tune your simulator,
that policy might be able to
transfer to the real world.
And then there was
also an example of--
in general, for manipulation,
send to real transfer
is a lot harder.
We're learning how
to do a Rubik's cube
that was trained in simulation.
And after about five
minutes of this rollout,
you get a Rubik's cube
that has been completed.
And that was with PPO.
PPO is also a common
choice for language models.
We'll start to discuss
them next week.